{
  "reference_number": "11770",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "One that is based on fairness, science,ensuring our country can continue to prosper and not emotion based rubbish."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The very fact that you are speaking about limits is rediculous. We should be basing our emissions on best practise for our different\n\n industries. If we have industries that are producing products with less emissions than any other country in the world then it is better\n they continue to produce products - rather than have people in other countries produce the same product with more emissions. You\n should be identifying industry standards and expect New Zealand Companies to be producing in the top 25 percentile."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "No spending money on other countries for their emissions - this is rediculous! Focus on our own country doing what we do well."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "We need to listen to scientists - not crack pot lunacy groups and the media induced hype. We need to focus spending our money on\n\n things that will really change the environment. Like the Kermadec Ocean sanctuary - you know that really world changing marine\n sanctuary our country could reannounce on if we were really serious about saving the planet - rather than just local projects that will\n\n have little, no or even negative impacts."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "I think if you want to depoliticise this then you should require a vote of 75% to put this in place or to change it. Barely 50% of\n government should not get to make far reaching decisions that will impact us after they are gone like this. Do it properly and work\n\n with all parlimentarians to get something nearly all agree to. At the moment it feels like the government is playing a bidding war with\n its coalition partners to get anything through - how about some actual agreement happening rather than paying each other off with\n\n promises."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - each incoming Government should have the option to review the third budget in the sequence",
      "answer_index": 14,
      "notes": "Of course new governments should be able to review all emissions budgets. IF you base it on lowering our emissions rather than\n working together as a whole planet then your emissions budgets will be useless. You need to get countries producing what they are\n best at producing with the lowest environmental footprint. Stop this egocentric crazy behaviour. We are awesome at agricultural\n\n production - the emission footprint of NZ milk, beef and lamb is way less than any country who are cut and carrying the bulk of their\nanimals feed. Why would you reduce our output - just to have other countries increase theres - when they will emit more gases than\n\nus? IT makes no sense. Aluminium smeltering with the use of hydro-power is heaps better for the worlds environment than the coal\npowered smeltering going on in India - we need to ensure that waste is also kept to a minimum (as this is as important as emissions).\n\nI am sure NZ are making somethings less economically than can be done overseas - althrough with our free economy we pretty\nmuch put a stop to that nonsense in the 80's. Focus on what we do better than the rest of the world in terms of the environment and\n\nprofit instead of imposing barriers that will mean our products will be made overseas in a less enivornmentally friendly way."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "The government have already set the considerations the Comission needs to take into account - you can't also put in timeframes -\nwhat if they are superseded by other considerations."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "You need to consider fairness. As a Dairy Farmer - I have had all of my grass removed from the Carbon Equation. There is a great\ncarbon cycle going on in the New Zealand Farming system. The grass takes the carbon fro the air, and stores it, the cow takes the\ncarbon from the grass and emits most of it back into the air. This makes the cow - a carbon neutral animal. What a brilliant invention!\n\nThe only time we add carbon into our farming system is when we use diesel or electricity. But the government has nationalised our\ncarbon credits for grass - turning our wonderful grass-fed cows into a carbon emitting unit. How is that fair? At the same time farmers\n\nall over the country are fencing and planting up our waterways. Do we get any carbon credits for all of these trees? All over the\ncountry waterways are benefitting from the financial investment being made by farmers - and yet the government decided that these\n\nareas are not significant enough to be considered for carbon credits. How is this fair? Why not encourage more farmers to plant their\nfenced off sections in trees, which gives our whole country a whole lot of benefits in carbon balance and water quality, by making\nripiarian planting count for carbon emission equations. Why is such a simple thing being overlooked? I think people are being\n\nnarrowminded by focusing on Carbon as a stand alone item. We need to be looking at the whole picture and how we can encourage\npeople to improve our environment instead of using big sticks, bully tactics, and media campaigns that attach hard working kiwis."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Don't we have the EPA? Aren't they here to \"protect New Zealand's environment and the people who live and work in it, for a better\n\nway of life.\" Surely they would be the ideal group to be looking at climate change as one factor in a whole lot of issues that impact on\nNew Zealand and its environment. Why are we wasting money on more offices, staff, and letterhead paper? USe what we have to\n\nensure that it is being looked at within the whole New Zealand Environment rather than one stand alone issue."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I do not know - as long as we stop sending money overseas instead of investing in our own country - I don't care who provides\nadvice."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Business Competiveness should be first on the list and is essential. We still have to run our country! Also we need to have a group\nwho are integral to any policy change - our own nudge group. Behavioural economists who are ensuring that things are implemented\n\nin a palatable way (get rid of that big stick people!) Representatives from industry, including actual farmers, not pen pushing\ncorporates - but actual farmers who are university educated, and/or expereinced in the practical side of life - such as Katie Milne,\nJacqueline Rowarth and I am sure there are some guys that would be suitable too. (Kidding - Doug Edmeades does spring to mind).\n\nOther major industries that are looking at significant impacts should also be represented. Technological experts should be employed\nas required - this will generally be covered by industry who will figure out ways to meet government direction."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I choose not to agree or disagree as that implies that I would then agree with the zero carbon bill to start with. I think that we should\nlet other groups who are specialised in dealing with particular issues should be left to do their job. Civil Defence are best at sorting\n\nout disaster situations. MPI already have controls in place for invasive critters that get into our country. Why not let the experts do\ntheir job rather than have a department of administrators get involved - that just spells disaster."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "I think you should let the government departments with the experts continue dealing with issues as they arise - and identifying and\n\nplanning for issues they believe are going to arise. We do not need a whole bunch of pencil pushers coming up with scenarios that\nmay or may not happen and then create a whole lot of paper work for others to do. Can we please focus on becoming a productive\neconomy rather than a bureaucratic behemoth!"
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Why? I see no reason to make industry share what could be sensitive and impact on competitiveness. The government needs to set\n\na fair direction and let industry meet targets in a way they want. Get the direction right and Industry will lead you there."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I think that Real Science, Technology, and Economics need to be taken into account. We need to approach this sensibly and start\n\nbeing a world leader again. It is crazy to reduce best practice production in one country only to replace it with high emission\nproduciton in another country. We should be focussing on doing things we can do well (in an environmental sense as well as an\n\neconomic one) rather than reducing our output just because it will make our overall targets look good. New Zealand is a leader not a\nfollower - get our diplomats back out there discussing helping big emitters to pull their socks up and adopt best practise. Start talking\n\nto the world about getting places to do what they are environmentall and economically good at doing. Share knowledge and\ntechnology with countries not able to currently adopt good practices and help them. Set our targets around being the best in our\n\nindustries (well at least in the top 25th percentile in our industry), rather than eliminating our industries. The focus should be on\nmaking the world a better place - rather than just New Zealand."
    }
  ]
}
